so let's talk about how we determine
what the block offset is and what the
block number is given an address let's
say that the processor produces a 32-bit
address with bits numbered from 0
through 31 so this is the address of the
location the processor wants us to find
in the cache the cache can be seen as an
array of lines each block size in size
in this example let's look at 16 as the
block size some bits of this address
tell us which block are we talking about
and some bits are telling us we're in
the block are we looking for our data
with the block size of 16 we need to
determine how many bits tell us where in
the block we are the block has 16 bytes
2 to the 4th is 16 so we need 4 bits to
tell us we're within a block we are that
means that bits 0 through 3 are going to
tell us once we find the block in the
cache which part of the block to read
the remaining bits bits four through 31
tell us which block are we trying to
find so these bits that tell us where in
the block are we going to find our data
are called the block offset and the bits
that tell us which block are we
interested in are called the block
number so what we do is we access the
cache trying to find a block according
to the block number if we find a block
we use the block offset to get the right
data from the block because there is
more than one location in the block